<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
  <title>greenplum_fdw (Beta)</title>
  <body>
    <p>The <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> module is a foreign-data wrapper (FDW)
      that you can use to run queries across one or more Greenplum Database version
      6.20+ clusters.</p>
    <p>The Greenplum Database <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> module is an MPP extension of
      the PostgreSQL <codeph>postgres_fdw</codeph> module.</p>
    <p>This topic includes the following sections:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><xref href="#topic_reg" type="topic" format="dita"/></li>
        <li><xref href="#topic_depend" type="topic" format="dita"/></li>
        <li><xref href="#topic_about" type="topic" format="dita"/></li>
        <li><xref href="#topic_using" type="topic" format="dita"/></li>
        <li><xref href="#topic_other" type="topic" format="dita"/></li>
        <li><xref href="#topic_limits" type="topic" format="dita"/></li>
        <li><xref href="#topic_compat" type="topic" format="dita"/></li>
        <li><xref href="#topic_examples" type="topic" format="dita"/></li>
      </ul>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic_reg">
    <title>Installing and Registering the Module</title>
    <body>
      <p>The <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> module is installed when you install
        Greenplum Database. Before you can use this FDW, you must register the
        <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> extension in each database in the source Greenplum
        Database cluster in which you plan to use it:</p>
      <codeblock>CREATE EXTENSION greenplum_fdw;</codeblock>
      <p>Refer to <xref href="../../install_guide/install_modules.html"
          format="html" scope="external">Installing Additional Supplied Modules</xref>
        for more information about installing and registering modules in Greenplum
        Database.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_depend">
    <title>About Module Dependencies</title>
    <body>
      <p><codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> depends on the 
        <xref href="./gp_parallel_retrieve_cursor.xml" format="dita"/>
        module.
        <note>You must register the <codeph>gp_parallel_retrieve_cursor</codeph> module in
          <b>each remote Greenplum database</b> with tables that you plan to access using 
          the <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> foreign-data wrapper.</note></p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_about">
    <title>About the greenplum_fdw Module</title>
    <body>
      <p><codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> is an MPP version of the
        <xref href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.4/postgres-fdw.html"
          scope="external">postgres_fdw</xref> foreign-data wrapper. While it behaves
        similarly to <codeph>postgres_fdw</codeph> in many respects,
        <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> uses a Greenplum Database parallel retrieve cursor
        to pull data directly from the segments of a remote Greenplum cluster to the
        segments in the source Greenplum cluster, in parallel.</p>
      <p>By supporting predicate pushdown, <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> minimizes the
        amount of data transferred between the Greenplum clusters by sending a query filter
        condition to the remote Greenplum server where it is applied there.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_using">
    <title>Using the greenplum_fdw Module</title>
    <body>
      <p>You will perform the following tasks when you use <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> to
        access data that resides in a remote Greenplum Database cluster(s):</p>
        <ol>
          <li><xref href="#topic_using/create_server" type="topic"
              format="dita">Create a server</xref> to represent each remote Greenplum
            database to which you want to connect.</li>
          <li><xref href="#topic_using/user_mapping" type="topic"
              format="dita">Create a user mapping</xref> for each (source) Greenplum
            Database user that you want to allow to access each server.</li>
          <li><xref href="#topic_using/create_ftable" type="topic"
              format="dita">Create a foreign table</xref> for each remote Greenplum
            table that you want to access.</li>
          <li><xref href="#topic_using/query_ftable" type="topic"
              format="dita">Construct and run queries</xref>.</li>
        </ol>
        <section id="create_server">
          <title>Creating a Server</title>
          <p>To access a remote Greenplum Database cluster, you must first create a foreign
            server object which specifies the host, port, and database connection details.
            You provide these connection parameters in the <codeph>OPTIONS</codeph> clause
            of the <codeph><xref href="../sql_commands/CREATE_SERVER.xml#topic1" type="topic"
              format="dita"/></codeph> command.</p>
          <p>A foreign server using the <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> foreign-data wrapper
            accepts and disallows the same options as that of a foreign server using the
            <codeph>postgres_fdw</codeph> FDW; refer to the
            <xref href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.4/postgres-fdw.html"
              scope="external">Connection Options</xref> topic in the PostgreSQL
            <codeph>postgres_fdw</codeph> documentation for more information about
            these options.</p>
          <p>To obtain the full benefits of the parallel transfer feature provided by
            <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph>, you must also specify:</p>
            <codeblock>mpp_execute 'all segments'</codeblock>
          <p>and</p>
            <codeblock>num_segments '<varname>num</varname>'</codeblock>
          <p>in the <codeph>OPTIONS</codeph> clause when you create the server. Set
            <varname>num</varname> to the number of segments in the the remote Greenplum
            Database cluster. If you do not provide the <codeblock>num_segments</codeblock>
            option, the default value is the number of segments on the local/source
            Greenplum Database cluster.</p>
          <p>The following example command creates a server named
            <codeph>gpc1_testdb</codeph> that will be used to access tables residing in
            the database named <codeph>testdb</codeph> on the remote
            <codeph>8</codeph>-segment Greenplum
            Database cluster whose master is running on the host <codeph>gpc1_master</codeph>,
            port <codeph>5432</codeph>:</p>
          <codeblock>CREATE SERVER gpc1_testdb FOREIGN DATA WRAPPER greenplum_fdw
    OPTIONS (host 'gpc1_master', port '5432', dbname 'testdb', mpp_execute 'all segments', num_segments '8');</codeblock>
        </section>
        <section id="user_mapping">
          <title>Creating a User Mapping</title>
          <p>After you identify which users you will allow to access the remote Greenplum
            Database cluster, you must create one or more mapping between a source
            Greenplum user and a user on the remote Greenplum cluster. You create these
            mappings with the
            <codeph><xref href="../sql_commands/CREATE_USER_MAPPING.xml#topic1" type="topic"
              format="dita"/></codeph> command.</p>
          <p>User mappings that you create may include the following <codeph>OPTIONS</codeph>:</p>
          <table id="umap_opts">
            <tgroup cols="3">
              <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="100"/>
              <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="186*"/>
              <colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="186*"/>
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">Option Name</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">Description</entry>
                  <entry colname="col3">Default Value</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">user</entry>
                <entry colname="col2">The name of the remote Greenplum Database user to connect as.</entry>
                <entry colname="col3">The name of the current Greenplum Database user.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">password</entry>
                <entry colname="col2">The password for user on the remote Greenplum Database system.</entry>
                <entry colname="col3">No default value.</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
          <p>Only a Greenplum Database superuser may connect to a Greenplum foreign server
            without password authentication. Always specify the <codeph>password</codeph>
            option for user mappings that you create for non-superusers.</p>
          <p>The following command creates a default user mapping
            on the source Greenplum cluster to the user named
            <codeph>bill</codeph> on the remote Greenplum cluster that allows access to the
            database identified by the <codeph>gpc1_testdb</codeph> server.
            Specifying the <codeph>PUBLIC</codeph> source user name creates a mapping for
            all current and future users when no user-specific mapping is applicable.</p>
          <codeblock>CREATE USER MAPPING FOR PUBLIC SERVER gpc1_testdb
    OPTIONS (user 'bill', password 'changeme');</codeblock>
           <p>The remote user must have the appropriate privileges to access any table(s)
             of interest in the database identified by the specified
             <codeph>SERVER</codeph>.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="create_ftable">
          <title>Creating a Foreign Table</title>
          <p>You invoke the <codeph><xref href="../sql_commands/CREATE_FOREIGN_TABLE.xml#topic1"
            type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph> command to create a foreign table. The
            column data types that
            you specify when you create the foreign table should exactly match those in the
            referenced remote table. It is also recommended that the columns be declared
            with exactly the same collations, if applicable, as the referenced columns of
            the remote table.</p>
          <p>Because <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> matches foreign table columns to the
            remote table by name, not position, you can create a foreign table with fewer
            columns, or with a different column order, than the underlying remote table.</p>
          <p>Foreign tables that you create may include the following
            <codeph>OPTIONS</codeph>:</p>
          <table id="ftable_opts">
            <tgroup cols="3">
              <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="100"/>
              <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="186*"/>
              <colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="186*"/>
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">Option Name</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">Description</entry>
                  <entry colname="col3">Default Value</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">schema_name</entry>
                <entry colname="col2">The name of the schema in which the remote Greenplum
                  Database table resides.</entry>
                <entry colname="col3">The name of the schema in which the foreign table
                  resides.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">table_name</entry>
                <entry colname="col2">The name of the remote Greenplum Database table.</entry>
                <entry colname="col3">The name of the foreign table.</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
          <p>The following command creates a foreign table named <codeph>f_gpc1_orders</codeph>
            that references a table named <codeph>orders</codeph> located in the
            <codeph>public</codeph> schema of the database identified by the
            <codeph>gpc1_testdb</codeph> server (<codeph>testdb</codeph>):</p>
          <codeblock>CREATE FOREIGN TABLE f_gpc1_orders ( id int, qty int, item text )
    SERVER gpc1_testdb OPTIONS (schema_name 'public', table_name 'orders');</codeblock>
          <p>You can additionally specify column name mappings via
            <codeph>OPTIONS</codeph> that you provide in the column declaration of the
            foreign table. The <codeph>column_name</codeph> option identifies the name of
            the associated column in the remote Greenplum Database table, and defaults to
            the foreign table column name when not specified.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="query_ftable">
          <title>Constructing and Running Queries</title>
          <p>You <codeph>SELECT</codeph> from a foreign table to access the data
            stored in the underlying remote Greenplum Database table. By default, you can
            also modify the remote table using the <codeph>INSERT</codeph> command,
            provided that the remote user specified the
            user mapping has the privileges to perform these operations. (Refer to
            <xref href="#topic_update" type="topic" format="dita"/> for information about
            changing the updatability of foreign tables.)</p>
          <p><codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> attempts to optimize remote queries to reduce
            the amount of data transferred from foreign servers. This is achieved by sending
            query <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clauses to the remote Greenplum Database server for
            execution, and by not retrieving table columns that are not needed for the
            current query. To reduce the risk of misexecution of queries,
            <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> does not send <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clauses to
            the remote server unless they use only built-in data types, operators, and
            functions. Operators and functions in the clauses must be
            <codeph>IMMUTABLE</codeph> as well.</p>
          <p>You can run the <codeph>EXPLAIN VERBOSE</codeph> command to examine the query
            that is actually sent to the remote Greenplum Database server for execution.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_other">
    <title>Additional Information</title>
    <body>
      <p>For more information about <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> updatability and cost
        estimation options, connection management, and transaction management, refer to
        the individual topics below.</p>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic_update">
      <title>About the Updatability Option</title>
      <body>
        <p>By default, all foreign tables created with <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> are
          assumed to be updatable. You can override this for a foreign server or a foreign
          table using the following option:</p>
        <dl>
        <dlentry>
        <dt><codeph>updatable</codeph></dt>
        <dd>Controls whether <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> allows foreign tables
          to be modified using the <codeph>INSERT</codeph> command. The default is true.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        </dl>
        <p>Setting this option at the foreign table-level overrides a foreign server-level
          option setting.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_costest">
      <title>About the Cost Estimation Options</title>
      <body>
        <p><codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> supports the same cost estimation options as
          described in the
            <xref href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.4/postgres-fdw.html"
              scope="external">Cost Estimation Options</xref> topic in the PostgreSQL
          <codeph>postgres_fdw</codeph> documentation.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_connmgmt">
      <title>About Connection Management</title>
      <body>
        <p><codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> establishes a connection to a foreign server during
          the first query on any foreign table associated with the server.
          <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> retains and reuses this connection for subsequent
          queries submitted in the same session. However, if multiple user identities
          (user mappings) are used to access the foreign server,
          <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> establishes a connection for each user mapping.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_transmgmt">
      <title>About Transaction Management</title>
      <body>
        <p><codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> manages transactions as described in the
            <xref href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.4/postgres-fdw.html"
              scope="external">Transaction Management</xref> topic in the PostgreSQL
          <codeph>postgres_fdw</codeph> documentation.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_limits">
    <title>Known Issues and Limitations</title>
    <body>
      <p>The <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> module has the following known issues and
        limitations:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The Pivotal Query Optimizer (GPORCA) does not support queries on foreign
            tables that you create with the <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> foreign-data
            wrapper.</li>
          <li><codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> does not support <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>
            and <codeph>DELETE</codeph> operations on foreign tables.</li>
        </ul>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_compat">
    <title>Compatibility</title>
    <body>
      <p>You can use <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> to access other remote Greenplum
        Database clusters running version 6.20+.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_examples">
    <title>Example</title>
    <body>
      <p>In this example, you query data residing in a database named <codeph>rdb</codeph>
        on the remote 16-segment Greenplum Database cluster whose master is running on host
        <codeph>gpc2_master</codeph>, port <codeph>5432</codeph>:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Open a <codeph>psql</codeph> session to the master host of the remote
          Greenplum Database cluster:
          <codeblock>psql -h gpc2_master -d rdb</codeblock></li>
        <li>Register the <codeph>gp_parallel_retrieve_cursor</codeph> extension in the
          database if it does not already exist:
          <codeblock>CREATE EXTENSION IF NOT EXISTS gp_parallel_retrieve_cursor;</codeblock></li>
        <li>Exit the session.</li>
        <li>Initiate a <codeph>psql</codeph> session to the database named
          <codeph>testdb</codeph> on the source (local in this case) Greenplum Database
           master host:
          <codeblock>$ psql -d testdb</codeblock></li>
        <li>Register the <codeph>greenplum_fdw</codeph> extension in the database if it does
          not already exist:
        <codeblock>CREATE EXTENSION IF NOT EXISTS greenplum_fdw;</codeblock></li>
        <li>Create a server to access the remote Greenplum Database cluster:
        <codeblock>CREATE SERVER gpc2_rdb FOREIGN DATA WRAPPER greenplum_fdw
    OPTIONS (host 'gpc2_master', port '5432', dbname 'rdb', mpp_execute 'all segments', num_segments '16');</codeblock></li>
        <li>Create a user mapping for a user named <codeph>jane</codeph> on the local Greenplum
          Database cluster and the user named <codeph>john</codeph> on the remote Greenplum
          cluster and database represented by the server named <codeph>gpc2_rdb</codeph>:
        <codeblock>CREATE USER MAPPING FOR jane SERVER gpc2_rdb OPTIONS (user 'john', password 'changeme');</codeblock></li>
        <li>Create a foreign table named <codeph>f_gpc2_emea</codeph> to reference the table
          named <codeph>emea</codeph> that is resides in the <codeph>public</codeph> schema
          of the database identified by the <codeph>gpc2_rdb</codeph> server
          (<codeph>rdb</codeph>):
          <codeblock>CREATE FOREIGN TABLE f_gpc2_emea( bu text, income int )
    SERVER gpcs2_rdb OPTIONS (schema_name 'public', table_name 'emea');</codeblock></li>
        <li>Query the foreign table:
          <codeblock>SELECT * FROM f_gpc2_emea;</codeblock></li>
        <li>Join the results of a foreign table query with a local table named
          <codeph>amer</codeph> that has similarly-named columns:
          <codeblock>SELECT amer.bu, amer.income as amer_in, f_gpc2_emea.income as emea_in
    FROM amer, f_gpc2_emea
    WHERE amer.bu = f_gpc2_emea.bu;</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>

